The American Speech Music. Change pitch on important information. What to do with
your mouth to sound American? One of the main differences between the way an
American talks and the way the rest of the world talks is that we don't really move
our lips. So when an American says, read my lips, what does he really mean? We
create most of our sounds in the throat using our tongue very actively. If you
hold your fingers over your lips or clench your jaws when you practice speaking
American English, you'll find yourself much closer to native sounding speech than
if you try to pronounce every single sound very carefully. If you can relate American
English to music, remember that the indigenous music is jazz. Listen to their
speech music and you'll hear that Americans have a melodic, jazzy way of
producing sounds. Imagine the sound of a cello when you say, Betty bought a bit of
better butter, and you'll be close to the native way of saying it. Because most
Americans came from somewhere else, American English reflects the accent
contributions of many lands. The speech music has become much more exaggerated
than British English, developing a strong and distinctive intonation. If you use
this intonation, not only will you be easier to understand, but you'll much more
confident, dynamic, and persuasive. Intonation or speech music is the sound
that you hear when a conversation is too far away to be clearly audible but close
enough for you to tell the nationality of the speakers. The American intonation
dictates liaisons and pronunciation, and it indicates mood and meaning. Without
intonation, your speech would be flat, mechanical, and very confusing for your
listener. What is the American intonation pattern? How is it different from other
languages? For example, if you hear a Japanese person speaking in English, the
sound would be very choppy, mechanical, and unemotional to an American. It's the
same with German peoples. It sounds too stiff. A man from Paris, on the other
hand, his Indonesian goes up at the end of every sentence and has such a strong
intonation that he sounds romantic and highly emotional, but this may not be
appropriate for a lecture or a business meeting in English. American intonation
do's and don'ts. Do not speak word by word. Bob is on the phone. If you speak
word by word, as many people who learned printed English do, you'll end up sounding
mechanical and foreign. You may have noticed the same happens in your own
language. When someone reads a speech, even a native speaker, it sounds stiff and
stilted, quite different from a normal conversational tone. Connect words to form
sound groups. This is where you're going to start doing something completely
different than what you've done in your previous English studies. This part is the
most difficult for many people because it goes against everything they've been
taught. Instead of thinking of each word as a unit, think of sound units. These
sound units may or may not correspond to a word written on a page. Native speakers
don't say, Bob is on the phone, but say, Bob is on the phone. Sound units make a
sentence flow smoothly like peanut butter, never really ending and never really
starting, just flowing along. Even chunky peanut butter is acceptable. So long as
you don't try to put plain directly onto your bread you'll be okay. Use staircase
intonation. Let those sound groups floating on the wavy river in the figure
flow downhill and you'll get the staircase. Staircase intonation not only
gives you that American sound, it also makes you sound much more confident. Not
every American uses the downward staircase. A certain segment of the
population uses rising staircases, generally teenagers on their way to the
shopping mall. Hi, my name is Tiffany. I live in La Cunha. I'm on the pep squad.
What exactly is staircase intonation? In saying your words, imagine that they come
out as if they were bounding lightly down a flight of stairs. Every so often, one
jumps up to another level and then starts down again. Americans tend to stretch out
their sounds longer than you may think is natural. So, to lengthen your vowel
sounds, put them on two stair steps instead of just one. Instead of, we're
here, say, we're here. The sound of an American speaking a foreign language is
very distinctive because we double sounds that should be single. For example, in
Spanish or Japanese, the word note is, to our ear, clipped or abbreviated. No. And
in standard American, no. Ending in an unvoiced consonant, one that you whisper,
t-k-s-x-f-sh. You'll notice that the preceding vowel is said quite quickly and
on a single stair step. When a word ends in a vowel or a voiced consonant, one that
you say, b-d-g-z-v-j-j, the preceding vowel is said more slowly and on a double
stair step. Unvoiced, seat. Voiced, seed. There are two main consequences of
not doubling the second category of words. Either your listener will hear the wrong
word, or even worse, you'll always sound upset. Consider that the words curt,
short, terse, abrupt, and clipped all literally mean short. When applied to a
person or to language, they take on the meaning of upset or rude. For example, the
expressions his curt reply, her terse response, or he was very short with us
indicate a less-than-sunny situation. Three ways to make intonation. About this
time, you're coming to the point where you may be wondering, what exactly are the
mechanics of intonation? What changes when you go to the top of the staircase or when
you put stress on a word? There are three ways to stress a word. The first way is
just get louder or raise the volume. This is not a very sophisticated way of doing
it, but it will definitely command attention. The second way is to stretch
the word out word that you want to draw attention to, which sounds very
insinuating. The third way, which is the most refined, is to change pitch. Although
pausing just before changing the pitch is effective, you don't want to do it every
time, because then it becomes an obvious technique. However, it will make your
audience stop and listen because they think you're going to say something
interesting.